<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xml:id="Edwidge_Danticat" xml:lang="fr" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Notice de Edwidge Danticat</title><author>Inès Burri</author><author>Anaïs Chambat</author><author>Célian Ringwald</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><orgName>Université Jean Moulin Lyon 3</orgName><orgName>ENS Lyon</orgName><orgName>Université Lyon 2</orgName><date>2020-01-19</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc>Notice et contenus associés à l'entité auteur dont les données sont issues de sites de références et de répertoires d'autorités</sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><div n="1" xml:id="Edwidge_Danticat_fiche"><person ana="Edwidge_Danticat" sex="na"><persName>Edwidge Danticat</persName><idno type="BNF">cb125106512#about<g ref="http://data.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/cb125106512#about"/></idno><listRelation><relation ana="Create_Dangerously" source="ile_en_ile_auto">Create Dangerously</relation></listRelation></person></div><div n="2" xml:id="Edwidge_Danticat_bio"><text ana="Edwidge_Danticat" ref="http://ile-en-ile.org/danticat/" source="ile_en_ile"><p/><p>Elle publie ses premiers textes dès les années de High School, dans le <placeName ana="Journal">Journal</placeName> de l’école où elle termine ses études secondaires. Elle obtient un premier diplôme universitaire (B.A.) à <persName ana="Barnard_College">Barnard College</persName> en lettres françaises avant de poursuivre, boursière, une <placeName ana="Maitrise">Maîtrise</placeName> en Beaux-Arts (MFA) à <persName ana="Brown_University">Brown University</persName>. Avant même d’être terminée, sa thèse en « creative writing » est acceptée pour publication. Le texte qui en résulte – Breath, Eyes Memory (traduit en français sous le titre Le cri de l’oiseau rouge) – a autant de succès auprès des critiques que du public. L’écrivaine a 25 ans.</p><p>La force et la texture du style de ce premier récit, où se croisent les réalités haïtiennes et newyorkaises, ont été comparées à celles des auteurs tel <persName ana="Maxine_Hong_Kingston">Maxine Hong <placeName ana="Kingston">Kingston</placeName></persName> et <persName ana="Toni_Morrison">Toni Morrison</persName>, et ont mérité à l’auteur un passage sur le plateau de la maîtresse du petit écran américain, <persName ana="Oprah_Winfrey">Oprah Winfrey</persName>.</p><p>Nouvelliste talentueuse, Danticat publie ensuite un recueil de ses courts récits, Krik? Krac!  Dans son deuxième roman, The Farming of Bones (publié en 1998 et traduit l’année suivante comme La Récolte douce des larmes), elle crée une fiction passionnante autour des événements tragiques de 1937. Danticat a également dirigé deux recueils de courts récits écrits par d’autres auteurs, dont The Butterfly’s Way, 33 récits d’haïtiano-américains. Dans toute son oeuvre, son regard sur l’histoire et sur l’actualité n’autorise ni le sensationnalisme, ni la pitié, examinant en particulier la réalité du peuple haïtien avec une prose limpide et enchanteresse.</p><p><persName ana="Edwidge_Danticat">Edwidge Danticat</persName> poursuit sa carrière d’écrivaine en se consacrant également à de nombreux projets sur l’art et la culture <placeName ana="Haitienne">Haïtienne</placeName>, comme l’indiquent ses collaborations avec les cinéastes <persName ana="Patricia_Benoit">Patricia Benoit</persName> et <persName ana="Jonathan_Demme">Jonathan Demme</persName>, et son engagement auprès de la National Coalition for Haitian Rights. Elle publie aussi des chroniques ponctuelles dans des revues telles que The New Yorker.</p><p>Parmi ses nombreux prix et distinctions, <persName ana="Edwidge_Danticat">Edwidge Danticat</persName> est lauréate en 1999 de l’American Book Award, pour The Farming of Bones, récipiendaire en 2009 d’une bourse MacArthur, la bourse dite des « génies », et du Prix Neustadt International en 2018 pour l’ensemble de son oeuvre. Traduite en français, son oeuvre a été couronnée notamment par le Prix Carbet de la <placeName ana="Caraibe">Caraïbe</placeName> en 1999, pour La récolte douce des larmes (The Farming of Bones) et par le Grand Prix de l’Association des Écrivains de la <placeName ana="Caraibe">Caraïbe</placeName> en 2013, pour son essai Créer dangereusement (<persName ana="Create_Dangerously">Create Dangerously</persName>: The Immigrant Artist at Work).</p></text></div><div n="3" xml:id="Edwidge_Danticat_biblio"><div ana="Edwidge_Danticat" n="3.1" ref="http://ile-en-ile.org/danticat/" source="ile_en_ile"><list subtype="ouvrages collectifs"><item>The Journal of Haitian Studies 7.2 (Fall 2001). »A Special Issue on Edwidge Danticat ». Articles de: Marc A. Christophe, Nadège Clitandre, Renée Larrier, Lisa M. Ortiz, Nadia Ragbar, Rodney Saint-Éloi, Helen Scott, Renée H. Shea et Helen Pyne-Timothy.</item><item>Antípodas (Journal of Hispanic and Galician Studies) 20 (2009). Nº special, Trujillo, Trauma, Testimony: Mario Vargas Llosa, Julia Alvarez, Edwidge Danticat, Junot Díaz and other writers on Hispaniola. Voir en particular les articles de: Sandra Cox, Pamela J. Rader, Marta Caminero-Santangelo et Stephanie Scurto.</item><item>Munro, Martin, éd. Edwidge Danticat: A Reader’s Guide. Charlottesville: University of Virginia Press, 2010. Dany Laferrière (foreward). Articles de: Madison Smartt Bell, Myriam J.A. Chancy, Maryse Condé, J. Michael Dash, Charles Forsdick, Mary Gallagher, Régine Michelle Jean-Charles, Carine Mardorossian, Nadève Ménard, Martin Munro, Nick Nesbitt, Mireille Rosello, Renee H. Shea, Évelyne Trouillot, Lyonel Trouillot, Kiera Vaclavik.</item></list><list subtype="études"><item>Casey, Ethan. « Remembering Haiti: Breath, Eyes, Memory ». Callaloo 18.2 (Spring 1995): 524-526.</item><item>Chancy, Myriam J.A. « Floating Islands: Spectatorship and the Body Politic in the Traveling Subjectivities of John Edgar Wideman &amp; Edwidge Danticat ». Small Axe 36 (November 2011): 22-38.</item><item>Charters, Mallay. « Edwidge Danticat: A Bitter Legacy Revisited ». Publishers Weekly (17 August 1998): 42-43.</item><item>Clitandre, Nadège. « Reformulating Haitian Literature Transnationally: Identifying New and Revised Tropes of Haitian Identity in Edwidge Danticat’s Breath, Eyes, Memory ». Journal of Haitian Studies 9.2 (Fall 2003): 90-110.</item><item>Clitandre, Nadège T. Edwidge Danticat: The Haitian Diasporic Imaginary. Charlottesville: University of Virginia Press, 2018.</item><item>Dufault, Roseanna L. « Edwidge Danticat’s Pursuit of Justice in Brother, I’m Dying ». Journal of Haitian Studies 16.1 (Spring 2010): 95-106.</item><item>Francis, Donette A. « ‘Silences Too Horrific to Disturb’: Writing Sexual Histories in Edwidge Danticat’s Breath, Eyes, Memory ». Research in African Literatures 35.2 (Summer 2004): 75-90.</item><item>Gannier, Odile. « Texte et contexte : les lectures plurielles de L’Autre Face de la mer de Louis-Philippe Dalembert et The Farming of Bones d’Edwidge Danticat ». La Lecture littéraire (Université de Reims) 10 (2009): 83-97.</item><item>Gyssels, Kathleen. « Littérature doublement exilée: Krik? Krak! d’Edwidge Danticat ». Ruptures 13 (octobre 1997-mars 1998): 187-202.</item><item>Gyssels, Kathleen. « ‘Couper le cordon ombilical’ : Edwidge Danticat, Marie-Hélène Laforest et ‘the French connexion’ ». Le Monde Caraïbe. défis et dynamiques (tome 1, Visions identitaires, diasporas, configurations culturelles). Christian Lerat, éd.  Pessac: Maison des sciences de l’Homme d’Aquitaine, 2005: 531-551.</item><item>Jean-Charles, Régine Michelle. « À travers l’Atlantique noire : L’imagerie de l’eau dans les textes des femmes haïtiennes ». Écrits d’Haïti: Perspectives sur la littérature haïtienne contemporaine (1986-2006). Nadève Ménard, éd. Paris: Karthala, 2011: 163-176.</item><item>Larrier, Renée. « ‘Girl by the Shore’: Gender and Testimony in Edwidge Danticat’s The Farming of Bones ». Journal of Haitian Studies 7.2 (Fall 2001): 50-60.</item><item>Marxsen, Patti M. « The Map Within: Place, Displacement, and the Long Shadow of Histor in the Work of Edwidge Danticat ». Journal of Haitian Studies 11.1 (Spring 2005): 140-155.</item><item>Meacham, Cherie. « Traumatic Realism in the Fiction of Edwidge Danticat ». Journal of Haitian Studies 11.1 (Spring 2005): 122-139.</item><item>Mead, Rebecca. « Stepmother Tongue ». New York 28.36 (20 November 1995): 50-.</item><item>Mortimer, Mildred. « Edwidge Danticat, Breath, Eyes, Memory: Rewriting Home ». Writing from the Hearth; Public, Domestic, and Imaginative Space in Francophone Women’s Fiction of Africa and the Caribbean. Lanham, Maryland: Lexington Books, 2007: 167-185.</item><item>Munro, Martin. « Langue, identité et postcolonialisme. Le cas d’Edwidge Danticat ». Trad. A. James Arnold. Critique 711-712 (août-septembre 2006): 694-707.</item><item>Munro, Martin. Exile and Post-1946 Haitian Literature: Alexis, Depestre, Ollivier, Laferrière, Danticat. Liverpool: Liverpool University Press, 2007.</item><item>Novivor, Ayelevi. « La pureté ou l’idéal destructeur dans Le cri de l’oiseau rouge d’Edwidge Danticat ». Relire l’histoire littéraire et le littéraire haïtiens. Port-au-Prince: Presses Nationales d’Haïti, 2007: 241-258.</item><item>N’Zengo-Tayo, Marie-José. « Children in Haitian Popular Migration as Seen by Maryse Condé and Edwidge Danticat ». Winds of Change: The Transforming Voices of Caribbean Women Writers and Scholars. Adele S. Newson and Linda Strong-Leek, eds. New York: Peter Lang, 1998: 93-100.</item><item>N’Zengo-Tayo, Marie-José. « Rewriting Folklore: Traditional Beliefs and Popular Culture in Edwidge Danticat’s Breath, Eyes, Memory and Krik? Krak! ». MaComère 3 (2000).</item><item>Putnam, Amanda. « Braiding Memories: Resistant Storytelling within Moth-Daughter Communities in Edwidge Danticat’s Krik? Krak! » Journal of Haitian Studies 9.1 (Spring 2003): 52-65.</item><item>Shea, Renee H. « Traveling Worlds with Edwidge Danticat ». Poets and Writers 25.1 (January/February 1997): 42-31.</item><item>Shelton, Marie-Denise. « Identité créole et mémoire: Edwidge Danticat et Fabienne Pasquet ». Journal of Haitian Studies 3/4 (1997/98): 103-108.</item><item>Shemak, April. « Re-Membering Hispaniola: Edwidge Danticat’s The Farming of Bones ». Modern Fiction Studies 48.1 (Spring 2002): 83-112.</item><item>Siméon-Jones, Kersuze. « Démences, psychoses et liberté psychique dans Le cri de l’oiseau rouge ». Écrits d’Haïti: Perspectives sur la littérature haïtienne contemporaine (1986-2006). Nadève Ménard, éd. Paris: Karthala, 2011: 149-159.</item><item>Sourieau, Marie Agnès. « La Mémoire engourdie de terreurs: The Dew Breaker d’Edwidge Danticat ». Journal of Haitian Studies 11.2 (Fall 2005): 94-104.</item><item>Suárez, Lucía M. « Breath, Eyes, Memory: Rape, Memory, and Denunciation ». Journal of Haitian Studies 9.2 (Fall 2003): 111-125.</item><item>Thomas, Bonnie. « Edwidge Danticat: Connecting the Political and Personal ». Connecting Histories; Francophone Caribbean Writers Interrogating Their Past. Jackson: University Press of Mississippi, 2017: 100ff.</item><item>Walcott-Hackshaw, Elizabeth. « Home Is Where the Heart Is: Danticat’s Landscapes of Return ». Small Axe 27 (12.3, October 2008): 71-82.</item></list><list subtype="interviews"><item>Anglesey, Zoe. « The Voice of the Storytellers: An Interview with Edwidge Danticat ». Multicultural Review 7.3 (1 September 1998): 36-.</item><item>Pulitano, Elvira. « An Immigrant Artist at Work: A Conversation with Edwidge Danticat ». Small Axe 36 (November 2011): 39-61.</item><item>Shea, Renee H. « The Dangerous Job of Edwidge Danticat: An Interview ». Callaloo 19.2 (Spring 1996): 382-89.</item></list><list subtype="en español"><item>Palabra, ojos, memoria. Damián Alou, trad. Barcelona: Ediciones del Bronce, 1998.</item><item>¿Krik? ¡Krak! Ramón González Férriz, trad. Barcelona: Lumen, 1999.</item><item>Cosecha de huesos. Marcelo Cohen, trad. Barcelona/Bogotá: Norma, 1999.</item><item> Tras las montañas. Mercedes Guhl, trad. Bogotá: Norma, 2003.</item></list><list subtype="en français"><item>Le cri de l’oiseau rouge (Breath, Eyes, Memory). Nicole Tisserand, trad. Paris: Pygmalion, 1995; Paris: Pocket, 1997.</item><item>Krik? Krak! récits. Nicole Tisserand, trad. Paris: Pygmalion, 1996;  Paris: Pocket, 1998.</item><item>La récolte douce des larmes. (The Farming of Bones). Jacques Chabert, trad. Paris: Grasset, 1999.</item><item>Après la danse. Jacques Chabert, trad. Paris: Grasset, 2004.</item><item>Le briseur de rosée. Jacques Chabert, trad. Paris: Grasset, 2005; Montréal: Boréal, 2005.</item><item>« Tante Denise, tu n’es pas gendarme, alors pourquoi cette fusillade à tes funérailles? ». Trad. Stanley Péan. Nul n’est une île: Solidarité Haïti. Sous la direction de Stanley Péan et Rodney Saint-Éloi. Montréal: Mémoire d’encrier, 2004: 155-173.</item><item>Adieu mon frère. Jacques Chabert, trad. Paris: Grasset, 2008.</item><item>Célimène, Conte de fée pour fille d’immigrante. (voir « Littérature pour la jeunesse » ci-dessus).</item><item>Huit jours: un enfant à Haïti. Illustrations d’Alix Delinois; Hélène Pilotto, trad. Toronto: Scholastic, 2011.</item><item>Créer dangereusement, l’artiste immigrant à l’oeuvre. Simone Arous, trad. Paris: Grasset, 2012.</item><item>« Claire Lumière de la mer ». Patricia Barbe-Girault, trad. Haiti noir. Textes présentés par Edwidge Danticat. Paris: Asphalte, 2012: 105-126.</item><item>Pour l’amour de Claire. Simone Arous, trad. Paris: Grasset, 2014.</item></list><list subtype="in het nederlands"><item>Adem, ogen, herinnering. Nicolette Hoekmeijer, trad. Amsterdam: Wereldbibliotheek, 1995.</item><item>Krik? Krak! Nicolette Hoekmeijer, trad. Amsterdam: Wereldbibliotheek, 1996.</item><item>Land voor de levenden. Nicolette Hoekmeijer, trad. Amsterdam: Wereldbibliotheek, 1998.</item></list><list subtype="romans / novels"><item>Breath, Eyes, Memory. New York: Soho Press, 1994; New York: Vintage Books, 1995.</item><item>The Farming of Bones. New York: Soho Press, 1998; Penguin, 1999.</item><item>Claire of the Sea Light. New York: Knopf, 2013.</item></list><list subtype="récits"><item>After the Dance: a Walk through Carnival in Jacmel, Haiti. New York: Crown, 2002.</item><item>Brother, I’m Dying. New York: Knopf, 2007.</item></list><list subtype="nouvelles / short stories"><item>Krik? Krak!  New York: Soho Press, 1995;  New York: Vintage Books, 1996.</item><item>The Dew Breaker. New York: Knopf, 2004.</item><item>Everything Inside. New York: Random House, 2019.</item><item>See also below – liens d’Île en île – voir ci-dessous.</item></list><list subtype="anthologies"><item>The Beacon Best of 2000: Great Writing by Women and Men of All Colors and Cultures. Edited by Edwidge Danticat. Boston: Beacon Press, 2000.</item><item>The Butterfly’s Way: Voices from the Haitian Dyaspora in the United States. Edited with an introduction by Edwidge Danticat. New York: Soho Press, 2001.</item><item>Haiti Noir. Edited by Edwidge Danticat. Brooklyn: Akashic Books, 2011.</item><item>Haiti Noir 2: The Classics. Edited by Edwidge Danticat. New York: Akashic, 2014.</item></list><list subtype="littérature pour la jeunesse"><item>Behind the Mountains: the Diary of Celiane Espérance. New York: Orchard Books, 2002.</item><item>Anacaona, Golden Flower. New York: Scholastic, 2005.</item><item>Célimène, Conte de fée pour fille d’immigrants (traduction en français par Stanley Péan, illustré par Mance Lanctôt). Montréal: Mémoire d’encrier, 2009.</item><item>Eight Days. Illustrations by Alix Delinois. London: Orchard, 2010.</item><item>Mama’s Nightingale: A Story of Immigration and Separation. Illustrations: Leslie Staub. New York: Dial, 2015.</item><item>Untwine. New York: Scholastic, 2015.</item></list><list subtype="essais"><item>Create Dangerously: The Immigrant Artist at Work. Princeton: Princeton University Press, 2010.</item><item>The Art of Death: Writing the Final Story. Minneapolis: Graywolf Press, 2017.</item></list><list subtype="textes et articles sélectionnés"><item>« A Rain of Daffodils. » Seventeen 53.4 (1 April 1994): 152- ; Literary Cavalcade 52.6 (March 2000): 4-9.</item><item>« Hanging With The Fugees. » Essence 27.4 (1 August 1996): 85-86.</item><item>« Forward. » The Magic Orange Tree and other Haitian Folktales. Ed. Diane Wolkstein. New York: Random, 1997: vii-viii.</item><item>« The Book of the Dead. »  The New Yorker 75.16 (21 June 1999): 194-.</item><item>« Bonjour Jean. »  The Nation 272.7 (19 February 2001): 20-22.</item><item>« Forward. » Walking on Fire: Haitian Women’s Stories of Survival and Resistance. Beverly Bell. Ithaca: Cornell U. Press, 2001.</item><item>« On Writing and Significant Others ». Journal of Haitian Studies 10.2 (Fall 2004): 4-8.</item><item>« Evelyne Trouillot » (interview). Bomb 90 (Winter 2004-2005): 48-53.</item><item>« Claire of the Sea Light ». Haiti Noir. Edwidge Danticat, éd. New York: Akashic, 2011: 115-138.</item></list><list subtype="traductions"><item>In the Flicker of an Eyelid. (L’espace d’un cillement.) by Jacques-Stephen Alexis. Trad. with Carrol F. Coates. Charlottesville: University of Virginia Press, 2002.</item></list><list subtype="distinctions littéraires"><item>1994     Fiction Award, The Caribbean Writer.</item><item>1995     National Book Award finalist, for Krik? Krak!</item><item>1995     Pushcart Short Story Prize.</item><item>1996     Best Young American Novelists Award, for Breath, Eyes, Memory by Granta.</item><item>1999     American Book Award, for The Farming of Bones.</item><item>1999     Prix Carbet de la Caraïbe, pour La récolte douce des larmes (The Farming of Bones).</item><item>2002     Prix Gouverneur de la Rosée du Livre et de la Littérature, représentante de la diaspora. Ministère de la Culture, Haïti, pour l’ensemble de son œuvre.</item><item>2005     Story Prize (first annual prize for a collection of short fiction), for The Dew Breaker.</item><item>2008     National Book Critics Circle Award (NBCC 2007) in autobiography, for Brother, I’m Dying.</item><item>2009     Best of Brooklyn Award, at Brooklyn Book Festival.</item><item>2009     MacArthur Foundation (« Genius ») Grant.</item><item>2011     Langston Hughes Medal, pour ses contributions distinguées aux arts et lettres.</item><item>2013     Grand Prix de l’Association des Écrivains de la Caraïbe, pour Créer dangereusement.</item><item>2018     Neustadt International Prize for Literature, pour l’ensemble de son oeuvre.</item></list><list subtype="enregistrements / recordings"><item>The Farming of Bones. Read by Rebecca Nicholas. Books on Tape, Inc., 1999.</item></list></div></div><div n="4" xml:id="Edwidge_Danticat_web"><list ana="Edwidge_Danticat" source="ile_en_ile" subtype="liens"><item>Edwidge Danticat, 5 Questions pour Île en île<ref target="http://ile-en-ile.org/edwidge-danticat-5-questions-pour-ile-en-ile/"/></item><item>A Conversation with Edwidge Danticat<ref target="http://www.bookbrowse.com/author_interviews/full/index.cfm?author_number=1022"/></item><item>Birnbaum v. Edwidge Danticat<ref target="http://www.themorningnews.org/archives/personalities/birnbaum_v_edwidge_danticat.php"/></item><item>Haitians in the City: Two Modern-Day Trickster Tales<ref target="http://english.chass.ncsu.edu/jouvert/v7is1/gyss.htm"/></item><item>Re-writing the Male Text: Mapping Cultural Spaces in Edwidge Danticat’s Krik? Krak! and Jamaica Kincaid’s A Small Place<ref target="http://english.chass.ncsu.edu/jouvert/v4i2/anpoon.htm"/></item><item>Random House<ref target="http://www.randomhouse.com/features/danticat/"/></item><item>« Simplement voir les choses »: la francophilie dérivée dans l’écriture d’Edwidge Danticat<ref target="http://www.tanbou.com/2005/FrancophonieDanticat.htm"/></item><item>Talk of the Nation<ref target="http://www.npr.org/ramarchives/ne7m0401.ram"/></item><item>The Nation<ref target="http://www.thenation.com/search/apachesolr_search/edwidge%20danticat"/></item><item>Dream of the Butterflies<ref target="http://www.thecaribbeanwriter.com/volume5/butterflies.html"/></item><item>Graduation<ref target="http://www.thecaribbeanwriter.com/volume5/graduation.html"/></item><item>Lost Shadows and Stick Figures<ref target="http://www.thecaribbeanwriter.com/volume6/lostshadows.html"/></item><item>Between the Pool and the Gardenias<ref target="http://www.thecaribbeanwriter.com/volume7/v7p66.html"/></item><item>Voices in a Dream<ref target="http://www.thecaribbeanwriter.com/volume7/voicesinadream.html"/></item><item>The Missing Peace<ref target="http://www.thecaribbeanwriter.com/volume8/missingpeace.html"/></item><item>We Are Ugly, But We Are Here<ref target="http://www.thecaribbeanwriter.org/ContrMainFrame.php?volsec=10036l"/></item><item>We Are Ugly, But We Are Here<ref target="http://web.archive.org/web/*/http://www.haitiglobalvillage.com/sd-marassa1-cd/"/></item><item>Quality Control<ref target="https://www.washingtonpost.com/lifestyle/magazine/quality-control-a-short-story-by-edwidge-danticat/2014/11/13/6fcf89c0-4f05-11e4-aa5e-7153e466a02d_story.html"/></item><item>Edwidge Danticat<ref target="http://www.macfound.org/site/c.lkLXJ8MQKrH/b.5458007/k.8D4C/Edwidge_Danticat.htm"/></item></list></div></TEI>