<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:id="Myriam_J.A._Chancy_biblio_auteur" xml:lang="fr" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Contenus associés à Myriam J.A. Chancy</title>
        <author>Inès Burri</author>
        <author>Anaïs Chambat</author>
        <author>Célian Ringwald</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <org_name>Université Jean Moulin Lyon 3</org_name>
        <org_name>ENS Lyon</org_name>
        <org_name>Université Lyon 2</org_name>
        <date>2020-01-13</date>
      </publicationStmt>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <div ref="http://ile-en-ile.org/chancy/" xml:id="Myriam_J.A._Chancy_biblio_auteur_ile_en_ile">
    <div subtype="livres">
      <list subtype="en español">
        <item>« Ayiti çé tè glissé: ocupación estadunidense y voces literarias femeninas » (extrait de Framing Silence). Casa de las Américas 233 (2003): 57-74.</item>
      </list>
      <list subtype="en français">
        <item>« Ayiti çé ter glissé: l’occupation américaine en Haïti et l’émergence de voix féminines en Littérature haïtienne » (essai). Trad. Catherine Pulling. Elles écrivent les Antilles; Guadeloupe, Martinique, Haïti. Eds. Joëlle Vittiello et Susanne Rinne. Paris: L’Harmattan, 1996: 17-36.</item>
      </list>
      <list subtype="en italiano">
        <item>« Il Suono Dell’Acqua » . Trad. Claudia Gargano. Il Tolomeo 14 (2011).</item>
      </list>
      <list subtype="romans">
        <item>Spirit of Haiti. London: Mango Press, 2003.</item>
        <item>The Scorpion’s Claw. Leeds: Peepal Tree Press, 2005.</item>
        <item>The Loneliness of Angels. Leeds: Peepal Tree Press, 2010.</item>
      </list>
      <list subtype="essais">
        <item>Framing Silence: Revolutionary Novels by Haitian Women. New Brunswick, NJ: Rutgers University Press, 1997.</item>
        <item>Searching for Safe Spaces: Afro-Caribbean Women Writers in Exile. Philadelphia: Temple University Press, 1997.</item>
        <item>From Sugar to Revolution: Women’s Visions of Haiti, Cuba and the Dominican Republic. Waterloo, Ontario: Wilfrid Laurier University Press, 2012.</item>
      </list>
      <list subtype="articles">
        <item>« Soul Searching » (with b/w photo, « Osborne Village »). proemCanada 2.1 (Spring 1990).</item>
        <item>« Sin Fronteras/Sans Frontières : Women of Color Writing for Empowerment ». Frontiers: A Journal of Women’s Studies 13.2 (Winter 1992/Spring 1993).</item>
        <item>« Black Women Writing, or How To Tell It Like It Is ». Canadian Woman Studies/Les Cahiers de la Femme 14.1 (Fall 1993); By, For and About: Feminist Cultural Politics. Ed. Wendy Waring. Toronto: Women’s Press, 1994; Rpt. Canadian Woman Studies: An Introductory Reader. Toronto: Illiana Publications, 1999.</item>
        <item>« Exile and Resistance: Retelling History as a Revolutionary Act in the Writings of Michelle Cliff and Marie Chauvet ». Journal of Caribbean Studies 9.3 (Winter 1993 / Spring 1994).</item>
        <item>« Léspoua fè viv: Female Identity and the Politics of Textual Sexuality in Nadine Magloire’s Le mal de vivre ». Writing the Nation: Self and Country in the Post-Colonial Imagination. Ed. John Hawley. Amsterdam: Rodopi, 1996.</item>
        <item>« The Black Female Body as Popular Icon”. Reading Over the Lines: Transgressive Readings. Ed. Georgia Johnston. Lewiston, NY: Edwin Mellen Press, 1997.</item>
        <item>« Brother/Outsider: In Search of a Black Gay Legacy in James Baldwin’s Giovanni’s Room ». Genders 26 (Fall 1997).</item>
        <item>« Marvel Women: Reading J.J. Dominique’s Mémoire d’une Amnésique ». MaComère 1.1 (Spring 1998).</item>
        <item>« Bridging the Mountains” (Commentary on Haitian/Dominican Relations). The Créole Connection (February 1999).</item>
        <item>« Of Hurricanes and Human Rights: A Case for Haiti ». The Créole Connection (Summer 2000).</item>
        <item>« Lazarus Rising: An Open Letter to My Daughter ». The Butterfly’s Way: Voices from the Haitian Dyaspora. Ed. Edwidge Danticat. New York: Soho Press, 2001: 223-239.</item>
        <item>« Recovering History « Bone by Bone »: A Conversation with Edwidge Danticat » (interview) Calabash 1.2 (Spring-Summer 2001).</item>
        <item>« The Heart of Home: Loida Maritza Pérez in Dialogue » (interview). MaComère (Spring/Summer 2003).</item>
        <item>« Diasporic Disconnections: Insurrection and Forgetfulness in Contemporary Haitian and Latin-Caribbean Women’s Literature ».  Beyond the Borders: American Literature and Post-Colonial Theory. Ed. Deborah L. Madsen. London: Pluto Press, 2003.</item>
        <item>« Facing the Mountains: Dominican Suppression and the Haitian Imagination ». Journal of Haitian Studies 9.1 (Spring 2003).</item>
        <item>« « No Giraffes in Haiti »: Haitian Women and State Terror ». Écrire en pays assiégé-Haiti-Writing Under Siege. Eds. Marie-Agnès Sourieau &amp; Kathleen M. Balutansky. Amsterdam/NY: Rodopi, 2005.</item>
        <item>« Subversive Sexualities: Revolutionizing Gendered Identities ». Frontiers 29.1 (2008): 51-75.</item>
        <item>« « Race » Travels in a Post-Genocidal Age: Witnessing and (Re)Counting Rwanda ». Cincinnati Romance Review 27 (2008): 1-15.</item>
        <item>« Writing Movement: On Being A (Caribbean Woman) Writer/Scholar ». The Caribbean Woman Writer as Scholar. Eds. Carole Boyce Davies et Keshia Abraham. Chicago: Caribbean Studies Press, 2009.</item>
        <item>« Outreach: Considering Community Service and the Role of Women of Color Faculty in Diversifying University Membership ». Over Ten Million Served: Gendered Service in Language and Literature Workplaces. Eds. Michelle Massé and Kathie Hogan. Albany: SUNY Press, 2010.</item>
        <item>« Border Crossings: Zora Neale Hurston &amp; Claude McKay’s Diasporic Travels ». The Harlem Renaissance Revisited: Politics, Arts, and Letters, An Anthology. Ed. Jeffrey Ogbar. Baltimore: John Hopkins University Press, 2010.</item>
        <item>« The Violence of Nationhood and the « Politicization of Memory ». Edwidge Danticat’s The Farming of Bones ». The Edwidge Danticat Reader. Ed. Martin Munro. Charlottesville: University of Virginia Press, 2010.</item>
        <item>« Nostalgie D’Amour: A Migratory Childhood » (memoir essay). CLR James Journal (Spring 2010).</item>
        <item>« Desecrated Bodies/Phantom Limbs: Post-Traumatic Reconstructions of Corporeality in Haiti/Rwanda ». Atlantic Studies 8.1 (March 2011): 109-123.</item>
        <item>« Floating Islands: Spectatorship and the Body Politic in the Traveling Subjectivities of John Edgar Wideman &amp; Edwidge Danticat ». Small Axe 36 (November 2011): 22-38.</item>
        <item>« The Aftermath » (nonfiction essay). Vandal Literary Journal 2.1 (Fall 2011).</item>
        <item>« Hearing Our Mothers: Safeguarding Haitian Women’s Representation &amp; Practices of Survival ». (abbreviated essay). Tectonic Shifts: Haiti Since the Earthquake. Eds. Mark Schuller &amp; Pablo Morales. West Hartford: Kumarian Press, 2012.</item>
      </list>
      <list subtype="fiction et poésie publiées dans des ouvrages collectifs">
        <item>« Andrew’s Universe ». proemCanada 1.1 (Spring 1989).</item>
        <item>« Je suis un nègre ». At the Crossroads: A Journal for Women Artists of African Descent 2.1 (Fall 1993); Rpt. Miscegenation Blues: Voices of Mixed Race Women. Ed. Carol Camper. Toronto: SisterVision, 1994.</item>
        <item>« Tou Pou Yo: An Excerpt from a Novel ». Fireweed 44-45 (Summer 1994).</item>
        <item>« Workshop, 1987 » et « Displaced ». Contemporary Verse 2.17 (Spring 1995): 4.</item>
        <item>« Hindsight » (short story contest finalist). The Louisville Review (Fall 1996/Winter 1997).</item>
        <item>« Ceremony » (short fiction). Black Renaissance Noire 1.2 (Fall 1997).</item>
        <item>« Do I move you? » (poem). Crab Orchard Review 4.1 (Fall/Winter 1998).</item>
        <item>« The Scorpion’s Claw » (a novel excerpt). Hayden’s Ferry (Summer/Fall 1999).</item>
        <item>« Photograph: Angel Island 1998 » &amp; « Heartline Cafe » (two poems). Litspeak (Dresden, Fall 2001).</item>
        <item>The Loneliness of Angels (excerpt). Il Tolomeo (Venise, Winter 2006).</item>
        <item>5 poems. Brassage: An Anthology of Poems by Haitian Women. Eds. Claudine Michel, Marlene Racine-Toussaint and Florence Bellande-Robertson. Santa Barbara: The Multicultural Women’s Press / UCSB Center for Black Studies, 2006: 62-71.</item>
        <item>« Dahomé » (poetry). Prairie Fire 28.1 (Spring 2007).</item>
        <item>The Loneliness of Angels (excerpt). Small Axe 24 (Fall 2007).</item>
        <item>« Dancing Words: Illness &amp; the Writing Process » (memoir essay with 12 photographs by the author). Calabash 5.1 (Summer/Fall 2008).</item>
        <item>« The Sound of Water ». The Massachusetts Review 51.2 (Summer 2010).</item>
        <item>Interview. Obsidian (Fall 2011)</item>
        <item>« Under/Water » (poem). Pawol Fanm, Special Issue of Meridians (Fall 2011).</item>
      </list>
      <list subtype="traduction par myriam j.a. chancy">
        <item>Swallowing the Wind, traduction du roman de Jan J. Dominique, Mémoire d’une amnésique (1984). Manuscrit inédit déposé à la bibliothèque de la Fondation Camargo (Cassis, France), 2001.</item>
      </list>
      <list subtype="prix et distinctions littéraires">
        <item>1998     Outstanding Book Award de Choice, le journal de la American Library Association, pour Searching for Safe Spaces.</item>
        <item>2004     Finaliste, Prix du Commonwealth (catégorie « Best First Book » pour la région Canada-Antilles), pour Spirit of Haiti.</item>
        <item>2004     Phoenix Award for Editorial Achievement, attribué par le Council of Editors of Learned Journals, pour le travail d’Éditrice en chef (2002-2004) de la revue Meridians: feminism, race, transnationalism.</item>
        <item>2011     Finaliste, Prix « Fiction » OCM Bocas en Littérature Antillaise, pour The Loneliness of Angels.</item>
        <item>2011     Guyana Prize for Literature, Caribbean Award, meilleure fiction, pour The Loneliness of Angels.</item>
      </list>
      <list subtype="sur l’oeuvre de myriam j.a. chancy">
        <item>Balutansky, Kathleen. « Framing Solange and Other Caribbean Women ». Feminist Collections 19.3 (1998).</item>
        <item>Bruner, Charlotte H. « Searching for Safe Spaces: Afro-Caribbean Women Writers in Exile ». World Literature Today 72.2 (Spring 1998): 435.</item>
        <item>Candelario, Ginetta E. B. « Voices From Hispaniola: A Meridians Roundtable With Edwidge Danticat, Loida Maritza Pérez, Myriam J. A. Chancy, and Nelly Rosario ». Meridians: Feminism, Race, Transnationalism 5.1 (2004): 69-91.</item>
        <item>« Chancy, Myriam J(osephe) A(imee) ». The Writers Directory 2011. Ed. Lisa Kumar. 26th ed. Vol. 1. Detroit: St. James Press, 2010: 398-399.</item>
        <item>« Feminist Forum ». Women’s Studies International Forum 20.5-6 (1997): I-VII.</item>
        <item>Gutiérrez, Laura G. « Latin American Womens Writing: Feminist Readings in Theory and Crisis / Framing Silence: Revolutionary Novels by Haitian Women ». Modern Fiction Studies 44.2 (1998): 419-24.</item>
        <item>Hinson, D. S. « Searching for Safe Spaces: Afro-Caribbean Women Writers in Exile ». American Literature 70.4 (1998): 916-7.</item>
        <item>Holloway, Pippa. « Searching for Safe Spaces: Afro-Caribbean Women Writers in Exile ». Journal of Women’s History 10.3 (1998): 217-.</item>
        <item>Horton-Stallings, Lamonda. « Granny Midwives and Black Women Writers: Strange Fruit; Plays on Lynching by American Women; Searching for Safe Spaces; Afro-Caribbean Writers in Exile ». Feminist Formations 11.3 (Fall 1999): 179-185.</item>
        <item>Jean-Charles, Régine Michelle. « The Sway of Stigma: The Politics and Poetics of AIDS Representation in Le Président a-t-il le SIDA? et Spirit of Haiti ». Small Axe 36 (November 2011): 62-79.</item>
        <item>Levin, Martin. « Cri de livre ». The Globe and Mail (16 July 2005).</item>
        <item>Springfield, Consuelo López. « Critics on Caribbean Women Writers of Fiction ». Feminist Collections 32.2 (2011): 1-5.</item>
      </list>
    </div>
    <div subtype="sur_le_web">
      <list>
        <item ref="http://www.myriamchancy.com/">Myriam Chancy</item>
        <item ref="http://www.amina-mag.com/16_anciensnums/magvisu455/amina_magazine455.html">Myriam J.A. Chancy, écrivaine et photographe</item>
        <item ref="http://ile-en-ile.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/icon_video-e1443203337462.png"/>
        <item ref="http://ile-en-ile.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/icon_audio-e1443200602532.png"/>
      </list>
    </div>
  </div>
</TEI>
